<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teams on ER Andrinopoulou</title>
    <link>https://www.erandrinopoulou.com/team/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Teams on ER Andrinopoulou</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://www.erandrinopoulou.com/team/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Pedro Afonso</title>
      <link>https://www.erandrinopoulou.com/team/pedro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.erandrinopoulou.com/team/pedro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pedro Afonso is a PhD student working on the following projects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;efficiently-analyzing-big-data-with-bayesian-joint-models-for-longitudinal-and-time-to-event-data&#34;&gt;Efficiently analyzing big data with Bayesian joint models for longitudinal and time-to-event data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Cystic Fibrosis (CF) is a lethal genetic lung disease that requires frequent monitoring. A commonly measured marker of lung function in CF is forced expiratory volume in 1 s of % predicted (FEV1). This sub-study stems from an international workgroup project to establish guidelines for longitudinal analysis of CF FEV1 using the U.S. CF Foundation Patient Registry, which contains health-related information for approximately 30,800 CF patients who collectively contributed 1,215,171 observations and 255,804 years of follow-up. It has been of clinical interest to model the association between FEV1 and time-to-death, but previous work neglected recurrent acute pulmonary exacerbation (PE) events and time-to-lung-transplantation, and mainly made use of smaller subsets of the registry data. Analyzing the entire dataset is expensive in terms of computation times. There is a need for algorithms that perform distributed analyses that simultaneously and unbiasedly investigate multiple correlated outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectives: Our primary goal was to investigate the association between FEV1 and the risk of PE, lung- transplant/death using all available registry data (2003-2016) for patients aged &amp;gt;= 6 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: We relied on the joint modelling framework, under the Bayesian paradigm, to simultaneously fit a joint model for a longitudinal marker, a recurrent event, and a terminal event. Due to the high computational time required to evaluate the entire dataset, we split the dataset into smaller non-overlapping subsets, parallelized their analyses, and then averaged individual posterior samples together. We explored different data splitting and combining strategies to get a consensus posterior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Preliminary results suggest that FEV1 is negatively associated with the risk of experiencing death or transplantation. The model obtained from the split data estimates an association of -0.11 (95%CI -0.13,-0.10), while the model leveraging the entire dataset shows an estimates of -0.11 (-0.12,-0.10). The 10-fold reduction in sample size produced a 90% decrease in computing time. The results were also investigated through simulation studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: The idea of distributing the Bayesian calculation is likely to be a useful solution to handle very big datasets without compromising the amount of information taken into account or sacrificing model adequacy, thereby, enhancing our understanding of CF FEV1 decline.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
